Well, this is it.
It's time we make this game by adding in some collision detection to detect if we crash into a car or
hit the sides of the road.
We will also be adding in a cool spin out animation to give it a more dynamic and dramatic effect.
But first, let's add in a dead simple crash detection.
So, moving to our main car sprite, we will grab the standard when flag clicked, then forever, then
F, and here we can add in this touching block and change it to detect obstacle cars.
And finally, if it does, we will have it stop all.
Well, that's simple enough.
Let's give this a go and see how it runs.
So, moving along the lines.
All is dandy.
And then if we say crash into this car here.
Well, there you have it.
Not bad.
So while we're at it, let's also check to see if our car is touching the edge of either land.
And we can simply do this by grabbing another two if checks a greater than operator and a less than
operator.
Then up in the motions group, we can use this exposition block which is the current x position of our
sprite.
So bringing that into both.
And finally, we can check if our cause X position is greater than or less than -185.
So adding a stop or into both of them.
And before we play, let's quickly see what we have going on here.
Basically, if our car is touching the obstacle car, we stop all and if our cars X position is past
195 or -185, which is past the edge, we stop all.
Okay, let's give this a try.
So as you can see, if we try to leave the road.
Well, our game ends.
That's what we like to see.
Now for the final touch, let's add our spin out crash animation.
So what we want is for our car to basically have a little animation where if we touch an obstacle or
if we go off the road, our car should spin.
I think the best place to start with this is in the motions group, because here we have this turn block
and if we click it here you can see our car turns.
And that's pretty much what we want.
So we can bring this block.
And then because we want it to turn a few times to make it look like it's spinning, we can grab our
repeat block.
So if we put this in here and you can see how our car looks like, it's spinning.
Okay, cool.
So now all we need to do is duplicate this block two times.
And then add it to each of our conditional checks.
And well, if we look at our script, if any of these conditions are true, like if if it touches an
obstacle car, it should first turn ten times and then stop.
So let's give that a go.
So driving down our road all is good.
And then if we hit a car, well that's not what we wanted.
It just turned for like a split second and faced back to the front.
But if you look at the code carefully, that makes sense because, well, this code is actually working
fine, but this code is interfering with it because this bit of script here is constantly getting our
car to point straight if we are not turning.
So this messes up our animation.
Now, one way we could fix this is simply dragging in this entire block of code inside this forever
loop.
And this way, these two scripts won't conflict with each other as if one of these conditions are true.
Like if we hit a car, the code won't move to the next bit of the script until it's finished, meaning
it will first play our animation and then stop all.
So giving this a go, you can see it works.
But this isn't exactly a clean solution as now we have two different types of scripts merging into one,
which can make it hard to understand and edit your code as you move forward.
So hitting command Z or the undo or control Z, what we can do instead is grab another one of these
stop blocks, but change it to stop other scripts in the sprite, then duplicate it twice.
And finally add it to the start of each of these conditional checks.
So if you look at our code now, if we touch anything, we will stop any other scripts in the sprite
running like this one here.
Then we will play the animation and then stop all.
And before we give it a go, let's just change this turn by to something less than like eight.
Finally giving this a go.
Driving down all is well then hitting into a car.
Well, there you have it.
Outstanding work.
This is very much a playable game and you should be proud to have got this far.
So sit back, relax and enjoy your accomplishment.
Because in the next section, we'll be looking at how we can transform this game with levels, dynamic
variables, sound effects, music, and a whole lot more.